this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
door / software hello I'm Jamey the
Spinelli's editor of the ethically
software tools of the trade column
interviewing Marcus welter a freelance
software consultant and coach
specializing on model oriented software
development domain-specific languages
and product line engineering according
to the profile on his website he's the
author of many books patterns and
articles but what he doesn't mention is
the breadth of cutting-edge software has
developed so Marcos Walter
welcome to the 200th episode of software
engineering radio hello glad to be here
it's a great pleasure to have you here
as a software engineering radio's
founder yeah for this very special
episode what do you mean with the bridge
of breadth of software I have developed
I mostly do prototypes and do consulting
there isn't a lot of software that I
actually wrote that still in use which
is said indeed a problem with software
that will add something we think it will
left for eternity and then three years
after we won't go back to the client and
we know that this has been superseded by
something else what struck me was that
it covered many diverse areas from
automation to embedded software to virus
other yeah things would you perhaps
please introduce yourself sharing your
background and interest with our
listeners well I mean you you summarized
it so about 15 years ago I finished
studying technical physics so I'm I'm an
engineer and I specialized in robot
stuff kind of it wasn't very practical
and I've always done software back in
the day I mostly the database client
software for a hospital for example to
do you know data management of which
doctor performed which things on which
patients and then after
I finished my studies I was started as
an independent kind of contractor at the
time and I focused mostly on enterprise
software middleware corba things like
that je when it came up and that's also
when I got in touch with the patterns
community Utah Eckstein was the path
through which I got through the Europe
lop to the Europe lob community he spent
a few years there I mean went to the
conference's for a few years and then
after a while I kind of moved from this
enterprise stuff to everything related
to modeling or started with UML based
stuff and then cogeneration I was
involved in the open architecture where
framework generator tool thing which
moved to eclipse and so I became quite
involved with the X text tool which I
never developed myself some people think
that I just was one of the early users
and I was consulting a lot for it and so
that's when I was introduced to textual
modeling also known as domain-specific
languages and essentially that's where
I've stuck since then I've used ESL's in
many different domains as you say
enterprise systems also financial
systems and the last few years I've
spent mostly in embedded systems where
we are building a set of languages based
on see essentially language extensions
of C for embedded software development
and that is not based on X text that is
based on NPS another language workbench
supplied open source by JetBrains
and so the last few years I've mostly
worked on designing and building and
implementing languages collaborative
languages that work together together
with C to develop embedded software so
that's kind of a short story and my
spare time I fly gliders and do podcasts
o quite many I say we know you mentioned
it secondly you mentioned that you
worked with domain-specific languages
for embedded products and also financial
applications and this is finally enough
areas that I've also applied the main
specific languages and I found this
fascinating where do you think these
specific areas and maybe other areas
where domain-specific languages are
particularly useful or pertinent yes so
I mean the question is I mean I could I
could reformulate the question by saying
I mean why would you use the SS in the
first place and what are the benefits of
using dsls and then you can kind of from
that you can deduce which which domains
are useful or our goods are suitable and
I think ESL's can be used for a number
of things one is simply automation right
you you ride a little bit of code and
then generate a lot of code so you don't
have to type as much that is the initial
motivation most people have because it's
kind of obvious you have to write less
and so you you don't have to work as
much so that's cool but when you spend
more time with DES else you notice that
there are other benefits that are maybe
more important because for example a
well-designed DSL allows you to capture
the structures and behaviors and all the
intricacies of a domain formally because
a language definition is a capture of a
domain structures and behaviors so a DSL
defining the DSL itself is even a way of
understanding a domain and when you do
that it acts as a communications vehicle
between the various stakeholders
non-programmers domain experts and
software people so it can be a an
integration backbone or a way of tying
down what it really is that that defines
the domain and finally if you have a
well-defined language you can often do
interesting analyses so even if you
don't generate a lot of code you may
still be able to prove the correctness
or analyze for example through model
checking whether a certain specification
expressed in some DSL has a certain has
certain properties and that that's a
benefit as well so from that it's quite
obvious that ESL's only work in domains
where you either are highly repetitive
so it's worth creating a language which
then allows you to write a little bit of
code from which you generate a lot of
similar code right that's essentially
the product line space or the space
where you have
a lot of bad frameworks but you have to
use you can generate the annoying code
to satisfy the frameworks but also
mentioned that yes Jade je was a good
candidate for that in the early days
right
many coach and writers started by from
simple let's say entity models
generating all the je e or j2ee as it
was called an infrastructure deployment
descriptors classes interfaces all this
crap you had to do at the time but other
domains for example the embedded
software domain for example we represent
state machines first class as state
machines and not as switch case
statements it's not necessarily a lot
less code you have to write but the code
is much more semantically related to the
domain and you could do model checking
you cannot easily do that on the code
unless you do code level model checking
but that's kind of a different story and
in this financial domain for example the
DSL was used as a way of well there was
this guy Herman who read who was 63 and
he retired he would retire in three
years or in two years and so the
insurance was quite pressed to capture
his expert knowledge into something that
other people can use and that was a
language definition and and the DSL
around it so that was another another
use case so domains need to be
structured I hate to use the word formal
because then people associate Greek
letters nothing against Greek letters
but you know what I mean right
formal provable Theory stuff but the
language that domain needs to be
structural enough so that it's useful to
have a kind of structured language to
represent them so the checking property
that you mentioned which I can also
relate to is a case of less is more you
have a smaller language sometimes
radically smaller language in which you
can express very few things and this is
useful because you can do actual
checking that is pertinent to that
domain could you give us some examples
and it's a bit counterintuitive that the
smaller language is a better than a
large general-purpose language in this
yeah yeah well um I'm not I mean I I
agree to what you say but I'm not sure I
would call it a a small language what I
would say is that that the concepts
relevant for the analysis you want to
run are represented in that language
first class right if you look at lists
before example there are not a lot of
concepts that list pass it has things
like lisps lists function calls and
stuff like that and whenever you want to
do anything that's more complicated you
compose that from these low-level
abstractions that means that anything
that's interesting to domain is made
from these atomic building blocks and if
you look at a program if an analysis to
look at if an analysis tool looks at the
program it has to kind of reverse
engineer the domain semantics from the
constructs that people build using these
low level elementary language
abstractions if you contrast that for
example with a language that lets you
directly write down state machines with
abstractions like state transition event
guard condition then you can very easily
map that to existing algorithms for
model checking that give you certain
guarantees about how the state machine
behaves so it's really about
representing things first-class now the
problem is really if you have many
different concepts in a domain and you
want to represent all of them first
class then you get a really big language
with a lot of keywords and that's
usually extremely ugly it's not very
flexible it's not very composable it's
very rigid and so that's where the size
of the language comes in if you can
manage to separate the overall structure
of a domain into several small languages
where each of them represents a certain
aspect of the domain with first-class
concepts thereby making it analyzable in
whatever way is useful to that aspect of
the domain and you can then compose
these languages to design or describe
the overall system then you win and that
is the goal let me give you another
a very simple example of how where this
what sometimes people call declarative
Ness thus first-class nature of
representing domain abstractions comes
in
imagine you have a very simple component
architecture DSL so you have concepts
like component interface and port where
components use ports to provide or
require interfaces so you could have a
pro a server component which provides
some database interface through some
port and a client component that
requires that same interface to talk to
that database now if you take two
components and compose them then a
client component connects to a server
component through these ports assume
some of one of these ports on the client
side is optional so for every given
component instance it may be connected
or it may not be connected to write save
code whenever you invoke an operation on
that port you first have to check
whether it is connected right
like if port P is connected then call
some method on P otherwise don't do
anything because if it's not connected
you can call it you cannot call an
operation now what you want is that when
you write code in your program that
talks to that port and you do not
enclose it in one of these checks like
if is connected then you want to get an
error message directly in the IDE
aesthetically and this analysis is not
so simple
if you have a general-purpose language
because you can surely map it into an if
but of course the if can do anything it
can say if port P is connected or true
right it can do anything so analyzing or
and then guaranteeing that really the
this this if around the port call really
does what you want guard against calls
on non connected parts is really tough
now if you have a DSL where you can do
things like the following you can say if
in an if statement in the condition of
an if statement you use this is
connected expression it cannot be with
anything else so either is connected is
the only thing in the if or it's not
there the
making this analysis is really simple
because then for every call and a part
you just check whether somewhere around
it there is an if statement that has an
is connected to that part trivial
one-liner but you can only do that
because you control the language design
and that that's kind of the key make
those things that are important to your
domain first class restrict the language
as you suggest that make it smaller in
that sense and then you really many of
the analyses are not as complicated as
they seem in the beginning in a
general-purpose language right and you
mentioned the Lisp before which is very
restricted language in one sense so
going back to your example from your
domain-specific language book what if
you restricted that a subset of Lisp
where you could only use specific
functions that had to do with that
domain and then you analyzed that Lisp
project
how would that suit the way you are
thinking about the SL design so first of
all I should say that I'm not another
Lisp expert and I always used Lisp as
the example for a kind of small language
with composable features and whenever I
say something some Lisp expert tells me
I'm wrong so I have to be careful what I
say okay that route for discussion of
between two people who both don't know
what they're talking about so I would
say if you if you actually could do that
if you define the bunch of Lisp
functions and you would statically know
what these are and you could tie certain
analyses to the names of these functions
then you you would get the same effect
however in a typical Lisp IDE
you cannot do that right I mean Lisp has
more stuff and you cannot easily
restrict things also you would rely on
the names of these functions because
then the names would carry the semantics
of what they imply exactly and and that
is usually a bad idea you don't want to
have analyses that rely on names but
again if if I if I use your example
where you would somehow maybe through
some kind of tool actually really limit
the names you can use you could argue
well then the names are controlled and
you can only use these ten and then I
guess it's almost like
which concept but I think that that's
really misusing this you just you know
use a language workbench to build a real
DSL if you want to do that right and
which brings us to the idea of language
the workbenches can you elaborate on
that many of our listeners maybe are
hearing the concept for the first time
so it would be nice to give them an idea
of what you mean by that and what it how
it helps us to develop domain-specific
languages yes
so I mean very generally at them a
language workbench is a tool or
framework or whatever you want to call
it that helps you build languages that's
essentially it I mean the term was
introduced by multi-info lore and I
think 2004 and he had a bunch of a
criteria what a language workbench you
know is and he had things like it uses a
schema to define the language structure
it uses projection 'el editing to define
the notation it allows to persist
incomplete or contradictory information
and so on and so he at the time when he
wrote that he was inspired by two very
specific tools one was in the
intentional domain workbench at the time
called the intentional programming
system child Simone is conscious money
right and also JetBrains MPs and that's
when he was inspired to write this in
the meantime there are other and in both
of these tools actually use projection
aletta ting and I'll come back to that
in a second
however in the meantime other language
engineering tools have evolved that use
parsers and that don't strictly comply
to what not in Fowler said at the time I
talked to him in the mean time a number
of times and I think he agrees that it's
probably a good idea or it would be a
good idea to loosen that definition a
little bit to probably say something
like a language workbench is a tool or
framework that lets you efficiently
develop languages and not just one
language but sets of languages that
collaborate that somehow interact where
for example one language
tens another one or where you can
compose existing languages and what's
important when you when you say that is
that from my perspective two things
first of all language definition isn't
just about syntax right what parsers do
it's also about type systems it's about
transformations to other languages about
maybe IDE support debuggers group where
version control integration refactoring
dataflow analysis there is a whole range
of things or aspects that you can that
are involved when defining a language so
language workbenches should help you
with all of these and also I think
language workbenches should allow you to
build arbitrary languages they should
allow you to build languages that you
would typically call a modeling language
so it's kind of high-level declarative
maybe even graphical and also they
should allow you to do what's typically
called programming languages so textual
and maybe fewer abstractions but highly
combined able and all of these languages
should be buildable or you know you
should be able to build these different
very different kinds of languages with
the same language workbench that's the
the real the end goal and there are
different tools that are more or less at
that point you promised you would talk
about projections so and so typically
when we when we when we write code right
then what we do is we type characters
into a text buffer literally I mean we
do that through fancy IDs
perhaps some people still use VI
whatever notepad but essentially we're
typing characters and that sequence of
characters is inherently unstructured
sure I mean every character has a unique
ID
I mean is it an A or I or o or 1s key
codes or Unicode codes but the sequence
is fundamentally at the beginning it's
undefined it's just a sequence random
sequence and then you have a parser
which takes a grammar where a grammar is
a definition of valid sequences of
characters it's a little bit more
involved but fundamentally and direct
the parser checks whether your sequence
you've entered correspondence course
to the sequence or to the allowed
sequences defined by the grammar of
which you claim to write a program or of
a sentence and then if if your sequence
matches then the parser usually builds a
tree representation of that sequential
set of characters and sure it organizes
things and it recognizes key words so it
built this abstract syntax tree which is
a tree like representation of the
structure that you have expressed
through your character sequences that's
how we know how this stuff works now a
projection Allah deter works differently
it works by the following principle
whenever you change anything to the
program like for example you if you from
your if you have the program that says 1
plus 2 and you make it 1 plus 2 plus 3
then whenever you type the + before the
plus 3 then everything you type directly
changes the tree representation of the
program and what you see is only a
projection or visualization or rendering
of the program so there is no parser
there is no grammar there is no
detection of valid sequences and then
construction of trees you directly
change the tree it's like a graphical
editor right if you're if you're in a
UML tool and you create a new class on
your canvas then you drag and drop a
class from the palette to the canvas and
it's not that the tool draws a rectangle
and then there is a pixel parser that
constructs the tree that the act of drag
and dropping the class creates the
object on the tree in the representation
of the model and then it's rendered
graphically or in other ways and
projection of editors generalize that
approach to arbitrary notations text
tables mathematical symbols you know
fraction bars stuff like that and
graphics and personally I think this is
a great idea and we can certainly debate
that the benefits and drawbacks let's do
that if I understand correctly a
projection 'l ater only allows you to
enter correct program sequences because
you edit a valid tree sometimes I find
myself working by pasting some random
text into the editor that I've copy
pasted from the web or something and
then transforming it through regular
expressions or editor commands into a
program body and this is not something
that seldom happens because we often
search for code snippets on the web or
some particular data that we want to
incorporate in our program as a
dictionary or a table and it's a
generally useful feature how does this
happen in a projection Elad etre well
first of all you did youdid directly hit
one of the disadvantages so that that
clearly isn't quite as simple but let's
make a few assumptions make this make
the assumption that the language you
work in is a language that also exists
in the parsed world like java or c or
something right
and that's quite likely because if you
want to find code written in some
language on the web as you just said
then it's likely that historically that
language has been used in a parsed
environment and there are parsers and
you know that is valid so imagine let's
make it concrete right you use Java in
MPs and PS is one of these projection
language work benches and it comes with
Java if you paste a snippet of Java code
that you that you copied from the from
the web into MPs then MPs actually
parses that on the fly and builds the
tree so it works as you would expect
however if you said let's say you paste
it some Java code or you copied some
Java code from the web that contained a
bunch of Java but also let's say a bunch
of soup bunch of pseudocode you know
whether you know person said you know
and here you do something like this is
that yes your line numbers yes or line
numbers right exactly
then you would run into a problem you'd
have to sanitize that first and so that
is that is that is a disadvantage
and yeah so right but there are many
benefits also and so it's a trade-off
whether you want to what you want to do
so there is perhaps you use another
intro to sanitize it into valid Java and
then you paste it into your for example
yes is there a specific instance of a
language workbench
that you would consider a representative
example a golden standard somewhere
where people should look into if they
want to begin experimenting with that
yes
I mean clearly jetbrains MPs it's open
source it's it's really good in terms of
editor usability because that has
traditionally been a problem because
some of these projection editors that
were very flexible but also extremely
annoying in the way you would you have
to use them like if you entered one plus
three you would first have to enter the
plus and then put the one on the left
and the three on the right and nobody
wants to do that and MPs has gone a long
way of making editing as text like as
possible not completely but we've just
recently run a survey with about 20
users they use different languages but
all in MPs and while we haven't
completely evaluated the survey in
detail what we saw so far is that most
said in the beginning it's a bit strange
but after a few hours or days depending
on the rest of the person they said it's
it's perfectly valid it's perfectly
works and that the point is nobody that
the point is that nobody says you know
projection editors are exactly like text
editors when typing they are a bit
different but the point is they're not
vers they're different and you can get
used to it and also you get a lot of
benefits right you can use notations
that you cannot have in past
environments like for example tables or
fraction bars and that's interesting for
dsls because sometimes your DSL should
be used by domain experts who have a
mathematical background and for them
it's more important to have a nice
notation then you know being able to
type 150 characters per second which
sometimes is what some programmers
charge there you know productivity by so
it really depends on what you do it's
also that projection of editors support
unlimited language composition
essentially you can easily combine
independently developed languages now
some parcels and some grammar classes
can also do that to some extent but only
to some extent and the extent depends on
the tool projection all tools don't have
that limitation so it's a trade-off
between notations flexi
ability and your expectation that you
want to continue editing code by typing
character sequences like you know for
the next hundred years what you did like
the last ten years right you know I
always think that if we would reinvent
programming today like starting from
scratch without any history then we
wouldn't limit ourselves to linear
sequences of characters I mean I
completely understand that there is all
this existing infrastructure and an
existing code bases and all of that and
so any other approach needs to have an
answer of how to integrate with a
textual world but if we would start from
scratch we wouldn't do it with this
linear editing thing and so I think
projection editing is really very
interesting for for certain domains not
for everything right and you you've
mentioned you wrote DSL for a state
machine I've done that probably with
both also written DSL for a user
interfaces and I wonder whether such
workbenches come also together with some
standard library that would avoid having
everyone writing their own little DSL
for a state machine or a user interface
or something like that whether you know
we are beginning to have something like
that or whether we expect something like
that to happen
so that's a very interesting question
because libraries are nice but a few
libraries or let's put differently
libraries are useful if they are
configurable and composable with other
libraries right if you would say there
is let's say some whatever complex
number library for C right but if you
use that library you cannot use any
other library because you cannot combine
them then the benefit of reuse would
essentially be completely gone right
exactly so traditionally if you look at
antler the parcel generator it has a
whole bunch of language grammars lying
around and you can of course download
that grammar and get started parsing C
code or parsing whatever other code
orders I'm sure there is a bunch of
grammars for state machine languages but
it's very likely two things one you
want to use this language exactly in the
way it was pre developed you may want to
change it a little bit and to you maybe
want to use that language in some
greater context together with other
languages and that's where this language
composition comes in and so if you are
able to let's say grab a language module
you know like a library and extend that
a little bit by adding two or three new
keywords in some way but then also use
that language or programs written in
that language with programs written in
another language in some combined way
then reuse becomes interesting and so I
think historically there have not been
that many languages in the way you would
like it in a library to get it from
somewhere because it's not that useful
you would hack it anyway you would
download it change it destructively and
then you know no updates would be
feasible and so on but with with modern
language workbenches where you have this
language composition or compose ability
and extensibility this becomes much more
useful and so for example over the last
of almost three years a bunch of
colleagues and myself we have built this
thing called and better and it's a set
of extensions to see for embedded
software development and for example it
has a state machine language it's
actually that language is an extension
of C that provides first-class for state
machines a first-class support for state
machines we have other extensions for
physical units or for software
components and interfaces or even for
specifying requirements or writing
software documentation and now the point
is that if you write a program and you
include that reusable state machine
language you can use it together with
the reusable units language and with the
reusable software components language
for example and you can also change that
language non-invasively you could for
example add new kinds of states or new
kinds of transitions talked yesterday
with a colleague about the ability to
add timeout transitions right you could
add these without Jake actually breaking
the definition of the original language
you could get them as a binary plug-in
and you could still extend them that way
and in your when you import a new
version of
the library you can still continue to
use your own exactly and unless the
library was changed in an incompatible
way of course of course right but but
the exchange ins are modular and really
that makes interesting the notion of
language modules that you can download
and use and so while what we've built is
not like general-purpose because it's
all based on C because that was our goal
and better is an example of a set of
currently it's about well it depends a
little bit on how you count let's say 30
extensions to see some of them big some
of them small and you can reuse them for
your purposes but then still adapt these
languages you know plus minus 10 degrees
or 20 to make them really fit your
environment and you can create
completely new extensions of C that are
specific to your domain and so these
things start creeping up because now we
have this meaningful ability or way to
reuse an attempt well 30 domain-specific
languages is quite a substantial amount
it's a larger than the first the library
that came with the first versions of the
C programming language so it's nothing -
it's something that you can actually
brag about yeah and what you described
before this copy-paste thing a way of
reusing the Mississippi languages is
certainly not a way to work but
interrupted you were about to say
something I forgot what I want to say
but for example what we've built is the
following if you take let's say if you
if you copy one of these state machine
things a state machine that you wrote in
am better MPs if you take that and paste
that to a text editor you it's it's
pasted a test text and you cannot easily
get it back into another MPs because we
have actually not built parcels for all
of these things because well if you can
discuss why but you can also paste that
when you copy it you can paste it as XML
and then you can send around that XML
and that XML is a representation of the
abstract syntax tree and that you can
paste into another MPs instance so we do
have the ability to let's say transport
program fragments through text
environments but we don't do it with the
concrete syntax but we use an abstract
representation and so that works for us
that's not the restriction we copy/paste
imagine we don't expect some text to be
and I have a different representation
and it works fine for the purposes of
that domain of image editing yeah let me
ask about the mentioned language
collaboration and I'm going what happens
when their concepts in one language that
are not expressed in the other there are
so many concepts within some language
like CR esoteric like exceptions or
closures yep so what happens then when
you try to assign or remove such values
from one language to the other
so let's distinguish different kinds of
different ways of how languages can
cooperate or collaborate or can be
composed the simplest way that has been
used for a long time is what I like to
call referencing so you write a program
in language a and you write another
program in language B and language B
contains some symbol which implicitly
references something in program a right
I mean the classical case is you have an
JSP page which contains declarations of
buttons and they have a given name and
then in the java class that backs that
JSP page you have essentially riri
declare java classes that correspond to
these page contents and then you can
interact with these things and so
essentially by name and type leanings
are connected right so in that case what
you said doesn't really apply right
because it's completely different
languages that have well-defined if you
will interfaces and expectations yes
that's exactly it's a good point because
in my example language B was developed
with knowledge of language a so they
have been developed together and they
can be made to collaborate okay
there is another composition scheme that
I like to call extension and an
extension what I just said is still true
a language extension if you have an
extension of some other language then
the extension has been built
specifically to extend some base
language a for example or shortcut ships
at sea because that's what we did right
we have a bunch of extensions to C so
for example our state machine
language directly uses SI expressions in
dart conditions and so since the person
who built the state machine language
already knows
si he can build the statement later
machine language in a way so that all
meaningful si concepts that make sense
for state machines can be used there
like expressions and guard conditions
and statements and actions that's how we
did it the the interesting situation is
really when you do what I like to call
language embedding where you have two
languages that have been developed
completely independently and you still
want to use them together and the
canonical example that people like to
use is let's say you have Java as your
general-purpose programming language and
then you have SQL to query your database
and now you want to embed SQL select
statement in Java and not as a string
because that would be cheating I mean
you would really compose the two
languages so that when in places where
you have let's say Java expressions you
can use a select statement now that's a
little bit of a strange terminology here
to get a value like a select statement
can essentially give you a tuple of
values from your database and you thank
for example can assign that tuple of
values to an array or a struct or
something like that in your host
programming language and here the
problem is you you you that the two
languages SQL and Java that have been
developed independently so nobody could
have thought about how to integrate that
into the other language and how to make
sense of potential incompatible language
concepts and so in that case the
solution is to essentially have a third
language that orchestrates the
collaboration between the other two so
for example you could have a language
SQL in Java which has a which has a Java
expression which contains an SQL
statement it would be responsible for
doing the mapping of types it would know
that if you let's say if your select
statement returns three strings then
then that then you can map that to a
string array of three elements or maybe
to a class with three fields or
something and it would also
that adapter language would also know
how to map the semantics in other words
your Co generator that for example then
maps your SQL to Java would know that it
would wrap that SQL statement into a
string pass it through a JDBC API and
then take a result set and somehow map
that to the to the Java expression on
the left side of the assignment so
that's kind of the general approach that
change with my experience there is no
Royal way you actually have to think
when you do such things it cannot happen
automatically no but you see the
important well one of the important
things is the following when you combine
independent languages and you do that
with let's say mainstream parcel
technology there is a high likelihood or
probability that the combined grammar
isn't even possible and you have to come
up with all kinds of escape symbols and
all kinds of things so on for one one
precondition to make this composition
work you still have to think in terms of
types and semantics but but but one
precondition is that you can't compose
at least that the syntax and that's
where modern parcels based systems like
the SDF parts are from University of
Delft and Amsterdam or generalised
parsers or projection editors come in
they are they don't just give up and say
ambiguous let's stop here they can
deal with wide variety details depending
on the tool of composed grammars
languages like Scala that actually are
designed in this way that allow you to
embed a DSL within fine where I go ahead
yeah I I'm I don't know I mean surely
there are languages that have syntax so
let's let's let's let's make let's step
on step back what I talked about so far
exclusively maybe except that Lisp
example you came up with are what's
called external DSL x' where your
languages are kind of defined through
another language engineering system the
language workbench so there is a set of
formal
at formalisms to define languages there
are also internal dia cells or embedded
dia cells where a language like Scala or
groovy or Ruby or maybe Lisp already
comes with facilities to define these
Elish things that can then be used in
the programs expressed in that host
language and Scala is one of the
examples that can do that to a to a
relatively large degree relative I mean
compared to other statically typed
general-purpose programming programming
languages it's not that great a degree
compared to let's say language workbench
approaches so if you say no you program
Scala and you know that there is a
little a little language that you need
to embed for example to deal with OSGi
services and you don't want to do that
with API calls and frameworks you can
tweak and enhance the Scala
syntax to a degree to create something
that looks like an embedded DSL and the
same is true for Ruby or groovy but you
usually don't get IDE support you don't
get type system check statically because
your ID and your type system your
compiler don't know much about your
extensions all meta programming in Scala
you can work with compiler plugins to
remedy some of that but your IDE still
doesn't know about anything about that
and so what language workmen just give
you is that they give you if you will
holistic extension that that includes
type systems transformations ideas
refactorings and all of that and I
really like to draw a relatively strict
boundary between using meta programming
in dynamically type or even statically
typed languages to create internal DSL
and kind of full-blown language
engineering that language workbench is
let you do that's when your book I
presume you focus on external DSL yes
and because you consider this approach
superior to well there are two reasons
for that first of all I've always done
external to yourselves I'm just not the
person to write about internal
yourselves I mean I can explain them to
the degree that I did now and I've built
about a bunch of hello world examples
but I'm really not an expert in that so
I wouldn't write a book about it but I
do think that for many of the cases
where you do you know we talked about
why you would want to yourselves
was about analyse ability stakeholder
integration
you know better IDE support and you
don't get these things from eternal
yourselves yes you get shortened syntax
and some stakeholder integration but
it's very hard to imagine to have an
internal DSL let's say for insurance
rule definition in embedded in groovy or
Scala and you then give that an
insurance guy who is not a programmer
right you can still get a job a ruby
file or Scala Fez and Ruby and Scala and
Java error messages which is one of the
major problems and you know no
first-class analysis so in my opinion
many of the reasons why you would want
to yourselves not naturally lead to
using external ESL's because you get
more benefits now of course there is a
big disadvantage you have to buy into
one of these language broad benches and
so if you just have a little extension
to a host language it's much more
pragmatic to just build an internal DSL
and most of these internal ear cells are
actually quote little extensions to host
languages and that's perfectly fine it's
just not what I've been working on let's
move one step back when I hand code I've
written in a general-purpose language to
other developers they just need to
understand my code and they can really
apply their experience in that language
to the code but when I hand them code
that I've written in domain-specific
language they also have to learn both
the domain-specific language and
understand the code yeah and the
situation's dragged on productivity how
do you feel about it when someone or
even you go and look at the DSL that
you've written ten years ago and maybe
it was interesting at the time but now
you have to relearn it to understand
what's going on yeah that is a trial if
you have to make but there are a few
things you should consider first of all
if you replace the word DSL with
framework you run into several some of
the same problems right if if you've
built a sophisticated framework years
ago and now you want to understand code
that uses that framework you have the
same problem if you want to teach people
to use a framework you still have the
same problem of teaching the people the
abstractions behind the framework how
they
work and how to use the framework so I
think the problem really is always
communicating the concept behind
whatever it is frameworks or or
languages and I would argue that
languages are easier to learn for the
following reason they are they're more
rigidly defined the IDE can give you
more support you get DSL level error
messages if something goes wrong if you
use a framework in the wrong way you get
a compiler error or run yes so so
assuming the person who you try to teach
it to understands the domain for which
you wrote your DSL or framework then I
would say teaching a DSL is simpler
especially if you use notations for your
language for your DSL that are already
close to what the people have worked
with so far and you can't do that with
frameworks if the people don't yet know
the domain well then the question is why
should they use a domain-specific
language for that domain right if they
are not in that domain why would they
use it same for a framework and so in
that case you would first have to teach
these people that the relevant to make
the concepts and I would argue that
doing that with a well-defined language
is easier now there is a risk that when
you define a language that you make it
unnecessarily different from maybe other
languages these people already know
that's a bad practice so just because
you can define weird syntax you
shouldn't do that so if you build
language extensions for C then you
should use C expressions and C statement
style wherever possible to not have
unnecessary learn efforts and especially
if people work in a curly brace world
then it's probably reasonable that they
expect your extensions of that curly
brace world to also be curly brace so
just don't make stupid mistakes but then
I think there isn't a big there is not
certainly not harder to teach or learn a
DSL compared to a framework here you
mentioned the notation which is
interesting because you then find people
like who wrote things like the sendmail
configuration file format which is
hideous
so it was successful for its various
might say nightmare how do you avoid the
situation of having something that's
clearly and maintainable well so first
of all I think we should distinguish two
scenarios or let's say many languages
distinguish between learnability
so they deeply the ability to pick the
language up for a newbie and the ability
to be productive and write code quickly
and efficiently once you've learned it
and many of these classical UNIX
configuration languages probably are
biased towards the product of the porter
the productivity and not towards
learnability
so that's maybe one thing you could
observe and many DSL are also targeted
to experts in a certain domain and you
expect that these experts use these
deltas else daily so you could say that
it's okay to define a language that's a
bit harder to learn because it's awkward
but then once you've learned that you're
extremely productive
I mean languages like APL are prime
examples of that now sometimes the
problem really is that domain experts
use TS else only rarely like they
configure a new mail server every three
years or they create a new insurance
plan only every four months or every
four weeks and in that case they never
really become you know routined
using the language and then it's much
more important that because they kind of
essentially learned it every time they
start up the program the IDE and so in
that case learnability is much much more
important and so maybe it takes them a
little bit longer to write the program
but since they forget everything until
they do it next time
it must be easy to learn so I think
that's a trade of you have to make when
you design a language and you have to
know what your users are like how they
work with a tool and that's really
important it's also important to
distinguish between what's usually
called right ability and readability is
it easy to write so you have to you know
few keystrokes essentially and is it
still easy to read and there are
scenario
where one person writes a program but
ten other people have to read it well in
that case readability is really
important if you do purl where you wear
one person typically writes a script
runs it for day or two and then throws
it away
I mean maybe simplifying a bit then
readability is irrelevant because you
don't ever read it again except when you
write it so it's been described as I
write only language exactly
so so you have to know these constraints
or this you know environment conditions
and then you have to define your
language appropriately there is
interesting things you can do for
example in projection Allah deters the
same language can have different
notations and you can for example in our
case you can project the state machine
as a table as text and very soon also as
graphics and then different stakeholders
can make different decisions and edit
the same thing different in different
ways and for example the textual
notation is much more writable but the
tabular notation for certain kinds of
things is much more readable because it
gives you a grid of events and States
and so you can easily do completeness
checks so some kinds of tools let you
postpone that decision because you can
change it afterwards but that's a kind
of special case so in your experience
how important is in practice the ability
to involve the domain expert do you
actually see domain X which who are not
programmers writing code or more reading
domain-specific language code or they
just expect someone else a programmer to
do it let's put it this way
traditionally dsls have been used in
technical domains where in some cases
the domain experts were the programmers
like for example if I have an
architecture DSL for je applications
then it's probably gonna be used the
language gonna be used by the same
person who writes a je code so it's not
really an involvement of actual domain
experts but this is changing for example
we've built a language for for
configuring refrigerator control cooling
algorithms and there the thermodynamics
person the physicist that dealt with
these control algorithms or cooling
algorithms was was actually involved in
writing these programs and also in
designing the language also in this
financial case this guy Herman who would
retire he was involved in defining the
right abstractions that go into the
language and then the users were actual
insurance I don't know how you call them
clerks for the wrong word people who
create and maintain insurance plans and
we're actually now building yet another
language in the insurance domain that
has the same kind of users so yes these
kinds of domain experts non-programmers
they are involved and sure maybe in the
beginning they need some help so they
start reading some of these programs and
more programmer types write them but you
know many of these people will start
recognizing patterns and getting what
you do and they like to be able you know
they like to be in charge they like to
be able to change you know insurance
plans without you know calling up the
programmer and asking them whether they
kindly have time to help them and that's
a strong motivation to learn these days
else and if you build them involving the
stakeholders in the first place you can
build languages that will be used by by
non programmers and I've seen it and
I've done it it's not necessarily the
simplest and default case but they do
exist
and it's hugely intellectually
satisfying when you get to the point
where you can have a non developer go
and write it means I think you have
succeeded in your DSL design yes and I
mean it's ridiculous I mean the way we
develop software these days is
completely ridiculous that domain people
take Word or Excel write down unchecked
imprecise inconsistent things and it's
not because they're idiots that's
because they don't have a tool that
checks for the consistency right and
then and then they print that or send
Europe whatever PDF and then a
programmer types these things into
low-level code I mean it's completely
obvious to me that some aspects of
programs the business logic should be
directly specified programmed checked
and tested by the domain people to me
that's so totally obvious and so we're
moving in that direction and that's
great given the right tools of course
so it's designing a domain-specific
language a skill that can be acquired or
do you require some type of talent yes
you have to be born a language designer
well of course it can be learned like
anything else I mean I let's put this
way that you have to be somebody who is
able to generalize to abstract a bit to
see patterns and and and then make those
patterns first class so I'm not talking
about programming these language
workbenches I mean these are just tools
that you can learn like any other tool
but thinking in in languages in in in
abstractions in meta stuff that that's a
skill you have to practice and there are
certainly people who are more example
oriented and think more in concrete
terms and and you know and other people
who are more generalizing who think
let's say you know in classes in general
classes or you know instead of saying
imagine you have a turbine with five
blades they already start you know
imagine you have a turbine with n blades
and M blades in the second phase and n
plus M is great well you know what I
mean so so I guess it's good an
abstraction abstraction things like that
so I guess if you're a good programmer
if you if you are good at for example
also implementing frameworks because
frameworks are also about you know
writing code for a whole domain or class
of problems then you can easily acquire
the skills of language design you still
need to practice the tools and you still
need to you know make a bunch of
mistakes in the beginning everybody did
that or does that but I don't think it's
rocket science not record science is
there anything else you would like to
relate to us because we're moving
towards the close of this interview well
I guess I should point out two things
first of all if you're interested in
that stuff you actually should pick up
my book it is actually a free PDF
download so you can easily pick it up
you can also buy a paper copy then it's
25 bucks or something and also I do
think that the MD and better stuff that
we've built over the last few years even
if you're not interested in embedded
software development it's a nice case
study of what
modern language workman's can do so I
usually I often demo it at conferences
and it's a great demo because it's it's
it's it's impressive what you can do so
even if you're not an embedded person
check it out read some of the papers to
get an overview of what modern language
workbenches can do and then pick up a
language workbench like MPs or spoof
arcs or X text or rascal or meta ate it
if you want to do graphical stuff and
and try it out these things these tools
have become quite sophisticated and
quite productive Marcus filter thank you
very much for your participation it's
been a pleasure having here well thanks
for having me on quote my unquote as a
radio high-five
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio net to support us you can
advertise su radio by clicking the de
crédit delicious or slash side buttons
on the site or by talking about this on
Facebook Twitter or your own blog if you
have feedback specific to an episode
please use the commenting feature on the
site so that other listeners can respond
to your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]